Guide to the Wyona S. Coleman Papers, 1971-2005 AIS.2000.21
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Longwall Mining, IV.
  - SMCRA- State and Federal, 1.
    There are two Acts referred to as SMCRA: one is a Pennsylvania statute passed in 1945 called the Subsidence Mine Conservation and Reclamation Act; the other is a federal statute passed in 1977 called the Subsidence Mine Control and Reclamation Act. Both of these acts have been through several attempts at amendment and this collection contains information about those amendments and the work surrounding them. One major attempt to amend SMCRA of 1977 is referred to as "State Window" Strip Mining Regulations. This was very controversial because it allowed states to create their own mining rules as long as they were no more or no less strict than the federal laws. Coleman and the groups to which she belonged were heavily involved in fighting this amendment and the papers reflect their work in this area.
    - Coal Legislation- House Bill (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Side by Side- PA v. Federal rules (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Notes on SMCRA History (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Title 25-, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Title 25 (Box 7, Folder 5-7)
    - Comments of National Wildlife Federation Ownership and Control Rule (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Background: Pennsylvania Subsidence Law (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Subsidence Rules 82-84 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - PA Coal Regulation Changes, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Areas Unsuitable for Mining Program (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - 1945 SMCRA (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - SMCRA (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - HB 329 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Acts 173/43 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - HB 1076 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Other Amendments to SMCRA 1945 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - SMCRA 1945- DER report (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - SMCRA 1977 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Enforcement of SMCRA (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - "State Window" Strip Mining Regulations (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - "State Window" litigation, 1982-1983 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Senate Bill 416 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Other Amendments to SMCRA 1977 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Senate Resolution 100 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - House Subcommittee of Environment, Energy, and Natural Resources Hearing, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Section 522 (e) of SMCRA- VER (Valid Existing Rights) (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - VER Opinion (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - VER (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - Office of Surface Mining (OSM) Reports, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 31)
    - SMCRA Litigation (Box 7, Folder 32)
    - SMCRA Litigation, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 33)
    - SMCRA Litigation, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 34)
    - OSM Proposal Revisions to SMCRA (Box 7, Folder 35-36)
  - Bituminous Mine Subsidence and Land Conservation Act (BMSLCA), 2.
    In 1966, Act 31, also known as the Bituminous Mine Subsidence and Land Conservation Act (BMSLCA), was passed in Pennsylvania. It addressed the damage caused to people and property by underground coal mining. Act 31 underwent a series of amendments, the most significant being Act 54. Throughout the legislation changes, Coleman and the groups in which she participated, mainly the Sierra Club and the Tri State Citizens Mining Network, were heavily involved in the deliberation surrounding the amendments and much of their correspondence regarding these activities is included in this section of the collection.
    - Pennsylvania Longwall Mining Regulations (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Act 31 of 1966 (Bituminous Mine Subsidence and Land Conservation Act) (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - BMSLCA (Box 8, Folder 3-4)
    - HB 2514 (Deep Mine Mediation Bill 1990) (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - HB 2514 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - HB 1828 (originally HB 2514) (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - HB 1828 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - House vote on HB 1828 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Deep Mine Mediation Program CAWLM withdrawal (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Other Amendments to Act 31 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Act 54 (Box 8, Folder 12-16)
    - Technical guidance- Act 54 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Act 54- DEP, DER (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Act 54- Public hearing, Oct.13, 1998 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Meetings on Act 54 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Comments on Act 54- Coal Caucus Meeting (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Flannery decision on subsidence, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Mining Litigation Correspondence (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - DEP's BMSCLA Regulatory Package (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - HB 2242 (Coal Community Fairness Act) (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Coal Community Fairness Act Rally, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - HB 2653 ("Peter Daley's Amendment") (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - HB 1800 Coalfield Water and Protection Act (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Court Cases and Other Legal Issues, 3.
    As a result of much of the legislation, Coleman and her environmental colleagues took part in several court cases. Many of these cases were about the legislation itself and what it would mean for future coal regulations. These groups also participated in court cases in which a person or group was in violation of the legislation that had been passed. The documents in this section of the collection reflect some of the extent of the groups' legal involvement.
    - HB 1075/Act 114 Valley Fills (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Hughes Hollow/Vesta Valley Fills (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Judge Haden Decision- Valley Fills (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Valley Fills- West Virginia 2002 Rule Change (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Mediation Working Conference (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Permanent Surface Mining Regulation Litigation (Box 9, Folder 6-12)
    - BethEnergy Mines v. Commonwealth of Pennsylvania (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Alice Water Protection Association (Box 9, Folder 14-15)
    - PUSH (People United to Save Homes) (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - PUSH Litigation (Box 9, Folder 17-19)
    - PUSH, 1999-2000 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Lucchino Case (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Roaring Run Court Case (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - Consol Pennsylvania Coal Company v. Commonwealth of Pennsylvania (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - Consultants (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - Pt. Pleasant Settlement, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 25)
    - Mine Subsidence Insurance Fund (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - Federal Register Notices (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - Release Agreements (Gag orders) (Box 9, Folder 28)
    - Other Lawsuits (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
    - Citizen Complaints- FOI/DEP Sample Letters (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Citizen Complaints-, 1982-1990 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - 84 Mining Company (Box 10, Folder 5-6)
    - Mine 84 Permit (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Mine 84 Permit Renewal (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Mine 84 Permit- Washington County, 1994-1995 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Mine 84 Permit- Perspective of Water Companies (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Permits (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Mettiki Mine- West Virginia Longwall Mining (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Hays Hill Proposal- Permit (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Shoemaker Mine Permit (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - 105 Permit (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - UMCO Mine Permit- Community Meeting (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - Willowbrook Mining (McConnels Mill State Park) - Permit (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - Hilsboro Coal Mining Permit (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - Enlow Fork Mine Extension (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - Baily Mine Extension, Greene County, Ryerson Park, 1997-2000 (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - Mining in Schuylkill County (Box 10, Folder 21)
    - DEP- Technical Guidance Documents on Mining (Box 10, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence- Greene County Mine Permits (Box 10, Folder 23)
    - Coal Combustion Waste Disposal (CCW) (Box 10, Folder 24)
    - Coal Refuse Disposal Sites (Box 10, Folder 25)
    - Gas Spill- Hazelton (Box 10, Folder 26)
    - Consol Coal Mines in Greene County, 1981-1993 (Box 10, Folder 27)
    - Pennzoil Underground Injection Control Permit, 1994 (Box 10, Folder 28)
    - RAG- American Coal Co. - Emerald and Cumberland Mines, Greene County (Box 10, Folder 29)
    - Maple Creek, Montour, Matties, Monview Mines (Box 10, Folder 30)
    - PA Regulatory Program (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Office of Surface Mining (OSM) Performance Evaluations (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - OSM Federal Oversight (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Ten-Day Notice Directive (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - OSM (Box 11, Folder 5-6)
    - OSM, 1997-1999 (Box 11, Folder 7-9)
    - Environmental Quality Board (EQB) OSM Hearings on Mine Proposals (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Intervention Department of Environmental Protection (DEP)/OSM Litigation (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - OSM/DEP Dispute (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Comments on DEP/OSM Proposal, 2003 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Final OSM/DEP Negotiation Settlement (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - DEP Amendment to OSM Decision (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - OSM Directives to DEP (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - OSM/DEP (Box 11, Folder 17-18)
    - OSM Inspection Reports (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - Mather Coal Refuse Pile (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - SB 1030- Renewable Portfolio Standard (Electric Generation) (Box 11, Folder 21)
    - Water (Box 11, Folder 22-23)
    - Clean Water Act- "Buffer Zone Rule", 2004 (Box 11, Folder 24)
    - Streams- Dunkard Creek, WV (Box 11, Folder 25)
    - Water Resources Forums, 2001-2004 (Box 11, Folder 26)
    - Probable Hydrologic Consequences of Mining (Box 11, Folder 27)
    - Stream Study- Enlow Fork, etc (Box 11, Folder 28)
    - Wheeling Creek Watershed Project (Box 11, Folder 29)
    - Watersheds- Settling Priorities Mon River Basin (Box 11, Folder 30)
    - Water Resources Symposium (Box 11, Folder 31)
    - Stream and Watershed Restoration (Box 11, Folder 32)
    - Watersheds- West Virginia (Box 11, Folder 33)
    - HB 866 Costs for Coal Mining Act (Box 11, Folder 34)
    - Oil Gas Act (Box 11, Folder 35)
    - Oil Gas Leasing (Box 11, Folder 36)
    - Noncoal Mining Legislation (Box 11, Folder 37)
    - HB 393- Strategic Lawsuit Against Public Participation (SLAPP) (Box 11, Folder 38)
    - HR No. 6- Sewage Sludge (Box 11, Folder 39)
    - National Coal Association v. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) (Box 11, Folder 40)
    - 1872 Mining Law Reform, 1979 (Box 11, Folder 41)
  - Bonding, 4.
    Under SMCRA, mining companies are required to pay a per-acre performance bond on all mined land. If the company fails to restore the land according to the standards outlined by SMCRA, the bond is forfeit and used to cover the cost of reclamation. Cleanup then falls to the "regulatory authority", which is either a state program or the OSM under a federal program. Some states have opted for a "bond pool" or "reclamation fund" instead of the usual performance bond system, which is permissible so long as the fund generates enough money to fully cover the cost of reclamation.
    Many environmental groups found that performance bonds and bond pools were inadequate and poorly utilized and accused OSM and other regulatory authorities of failing to follow SMCRA guidelines. This led to extensive lawsuits throughout the 1980s and late 1990s, often involving multiple plaintiffs and defendants.
    - Applicant Violator System (AVS) (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Reg- 8 Oversight of State Regulatory Programs (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Review of Bonding System (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Coal Forfeiture Sites (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Bonding- Articles/Clippings/News releases (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Bonding Legislation, 1980s (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Full Cost Bonding Draft, 1999 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Bonding Suits, 1980s (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Bonding Suits (PFSC v. Hess), 1999-2002 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Research- Bonding Permits by State, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Bonding Suit Mailing Lists, 1999 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Suit Against OSM-2003 (PA Bond Program Approval) (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence- Bonding, 1999-2003 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Alternative Bonding System 1991 (Justification for 1999 suit) (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Bonding Suits (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Bonding Suits (Penn Future/DEP), 1999 (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - Bonding Suits (Penn Future/DEP), 1999-2002 (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Bonding Legislation Research, 1999-2000 (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - Bonding Suit-, 1981 (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - Reports on Bonding by DEP, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 20)
    - Witness Questionnaires, 1999-2000 (Box 12, Folder 21)
    - PFSC, et al. v. Norton, et al., 2005 (Box 12, Folder 22)
    - Abandoned Mined Lands (AML) (Box 12, Folder 23)
    - AML Program/Fund (Box 12, Folder 24-25)
    - Abandoned Mined Lands/ Acid Mine Drainage (Box 12, Folder 26)
    - HB 1427 Mine Drainage Cleanup Act, 1997 (Box 12, Folder 27)
    - Acid Mine Drainage Workshop, 1994 (Box 12, Folder 28)
  - Groups, 5.
    Many environmental groups strived for better mining regulations. Although the Pennsylvania Chapter of the Sierra Club's focus was wide-ranging, other groups, such as the Tri-State Citizens Mining Network and the Citizens Coal Council, were formed specifically to minimize damage caused by mining. The groups often worked together to achieve their goals, forming alliances and committees to address specific problems. Their efforts are documented here through meeting minutes, correspondence, committee and workshop information, and group publications.
    - Sierra Club (SC), 1980-2001 (Box 13, Folder 1-6)
    - Budgets, 1992-1997 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Centennial (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Funding Campaign (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - PA Chapter Testimony and Comment (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Energy Committee, 1983-1994 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Department of Environmental Resources (DER)-Proposal Division (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Jobs v. the Environment (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Sierra Club Foundation (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - Sierra Club and Minorities- Cultural Diversity (Box 13, Folder 16)
    - Conservation Committee, 1989-1996 (Box 13, Folder 17-18)
    - Legal Committee (Box 13, Folder 19)
    - Training/Workshop (Box 13, Folder 20)
    - Leaders, May 1995 (Box 13, Folder 21)
    - Environmental Petition and Green Agenda (Box 13, Folder 22)
    - Fifth Annual Environmental Justice In-Gathering, 2004 (Box 13, Folder 23)
    - Pennsylvania Sierra Club Mining Committee, 2001-2005 (Box 13, Folder 24)
    - Conflict Resolution, 1997 (Box 13, Folder 25)
    - Coal Policy (Box 13, Folder 26)
    - "Dump Watt" Drive, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 27)
    - Legal Fees - Richard Ehman (Box 13, Folder 28)
    - Grant Information (Box 13, Folder 29)
    - Alfred G. Etter (Box 13, Folder 30)
    - Publications (Box 13, Folder 31)
    - Group Directories (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Tri-State By-Laws (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Tri-State, 1994-2002 (Box 14, Folder 3-4)
    - Tri-State Meetings and Activities (Box 14, Folder 5-6)
    - Tri-State Meeting Notes (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Tri-State Planning Retreat (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Tri-State Underground Mining Workshop, Aug. 2005 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Tri-State Grant Information (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Tri-State Newsletters (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - General Tri-State Correspondence (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Tri-State and Act 54 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Tri-State and the 84 Mining Company (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Tri-State and Water (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Tri-State and OSM (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - Tri-State and SMCRA (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - National Citizen's Coal Law Project (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Concerned About Water Loss Due to Mining (CAWLM) (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - Mining and Reclamation Advisory Board (MRAB) of DEP (Box 14, Folder 20)
    - Appalachian Regional Conservation Committee (ARCC), 2004 (Box 14, Folder 21)
    - Ten Mile Protection Network (Box 14, Folder 22)
    - Citizens Organized Against Longwalling (COAL) (Box 14, Folder 23)
    - Coalfield Justice Coalition (Box 14, Folder 24)
    - Coal Justice Alliance (Box 14, Folder 25)
    - Public Employees for Environmental Responsibility (PEER) (Box 14, Folder 26)
    - Pennsylvania Environmental Defense Foundation (Box 14, Folder 27)
    - Environmental Quality Board (Box 14, Folder 28)
    - Citizen's Coal Council (CCC), 1994-2001 (Box 14, Folder 29-33)
    - Learning About Organizing - CCC Workshop (Box 14, Folder 34)
    - Justice in the Coalfields of Appalachia - CCC Conference (Box 14, Folder 35)
    - Coal Summit - Lexington KY, 1987 (Box 14, Folder 36)
    - Coal Summit, 2002 (Box 14, Folder 37)
    - Coal Summit Follow-up (Box 14, Folder 38)
    - DER Policies and Roundtables, 2000 (Box 14, Folder 39)
    - DEP Mining and Reclamation Advisory Board - Meetings (Box 14, Folder 40)
    - DEP Informational Roundtable (Box 14, Folder 41)
    - High Extraction Mining Forum, 1997 (Box 14, Folder 42)
    - Vision Workshop, 2001 (Box 14, Folder 43)
    - Workshops/Conferences - Other (Box 14, Folder 44)
    - Awards (Box 14, Folder 45)
    - Mine Tour - Fayette and Somerset Counties (Box 14, Folder 46)
    - Enlow Mining Tour Photos (Box 14, Folder 47)
    - Mining Tours (Box 14, Folder 48)
    - Correspondence and Other Activist Groups (Box 14, Folder 49)
    - Other Groups (Box 14, Folder 50)
    - Other Group Publications (Box 14, Folder 51)
- Research, V.
  Coleman collected clippings, articles, reports, and studies on a wide variety of topics relevant to mining and environmental protection in general. These files are organized alphabetically.
  - Abandoned Mine Land (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Abandoned Mine Pool Study (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Acid Mine Drainage (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Acid Rain (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Activism Advice (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Air Pollution (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Alternate Energy Technology (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Alternative Energy (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Articles for Coal Newsletter Edition (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Ash (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - An Assessment of Managing Strategies to Reduce Waste Quantities (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Bark Camp Mine Reclamation (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Beneficial Use of Mining Sites and Waste (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Blasting (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Blasting Vibrations (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Blasting Workshop, Nov. 4, 1995 (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Bonding (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - British Regulations on Subsidence (Box 15, Folder 18)
  - Bush Administration and Environmental Law (Box 15, Folder 19)
  - Coal Combustion Waste (Box 15, Folder 20)
  - Coal Power Resurgence (Box 15, Folder 21)
  - Consol Energy Co. (Box 15, Folder 22)
  - Corporate Research (Box 15, Folder 23)
  - DEP (Box 15, Folder 24)
  - DEP Studies (Box 15, Folder 25)
  - DER (Box 15, Folder 26)
  - DER, DEP, Department of the Interior (Box 15, Folder 27)
  - Eco Terrorism (Box 15, Folder 28)
  - Energy, 1974-1981 (Box 15, Folder 29)
  - Enlow Fork Fall 1998 Biomonitoring Report (Box 15, Folder 30)
  - Environmental Justice (Box 15, Folder 31)
  - EPA and Aging, "Senior Death Discount" (Box 15, Folder 32)
  - Fact Sheets (Box 15, Folder 33)
  - Global Warming (Box 15, Folder 34-35)
  - Green Power Campaign (Box 15, Folder 36)
  - Greene County Severance Tax (Box 15, Folder 37)
  - Greenpeace (Box 15, Folder 38)
  - "Growing Greener" Plan (Box 15, Folder 39)
  - Hard Rock Mining (Box 15, Folder 40)
  - Illinois Mining (Box 15, Folder 41)
  - "King Coal" (Box 15, Folder 42)
  - Legal (Box 15, Folder 43)
  - Longwall Mining (Box 15, Folder 44)
  - Longwall Mining Damage (Box 15, Folder 45)
  - Longwall Mining Studies (Box 15, Folder 46-47)
  - Mercury (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Methane (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Mine Fires (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Mine Safety (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Minerals in Allegheny National Forest (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Mining Economics (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Mining - General (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Monongahela Basin Mine Pool Project, 2001 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Mountain Top Removal (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - National Coal Policy Project (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Natural Resources Tax (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Network Demo, Jan. 19, 2001 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Nuclear Power Information (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Ohio Mining (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - OSM (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - OSM Study on CHIA's (Box 16, Folder 16)
  - Other Issues (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - Pennsylvania State Forests (Box 16, Folder 18)
  - Power Plants (Box 16, Folder 19)
  - Quecreek Mine Rescue (Box 16, Folder 20)
  - Report of the Pennsylvania 21st Century Environment Commission and Responses (Box 16, Folder 21)
  - Reports (Box 16, Folder 22)
  - Robinson Township - Waste Coal Plant (Box 16, Folder 23)
  - Siting Hazardous Waste Facilities, 1981 (Box 16, Folder 24)
  - SLAPP Suits (Box 16, Folder 25)
  - Sludge (Box 16, Folder 26)
  - Strip Mining (Box 16, Folder 27)
  - Supplemental C and other Misc (Box 16, Folder 28)
  - Taxation - Mining Assets, Coal Economics, 1996 (Box 16, Folder 29)
  - Technology (Box 16, Folder 30)
  - Trash/Recycling (Box 16, Folder 31)
  - Valley Fills (Box 16, Folder 32)
  - Water (Box 16, Folder 33)
  - Waste (Box 16, Folder 34)
  - West Virginia Mining (Box 16, Folder 35)
  - Western Issues (Box 16, Folder 36)
  - Wetlands (Box 16, Folder 37)
  - Wildlife and Parks (Box 16, Folder 38)
  - Agriculture (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Backstowing (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Brandon's Hunger Strike (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Campaign Finance Reform: House Bill #584 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Citizen Complaints, 1998-2002 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Clean Coal Technology and Renewable Energy (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Coal and the "Energy Crisis" (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Coal Bed Methane (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Coal Combustion Waste (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Coal Gasification (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Coal Industry (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Coal Refuse Disposal Facilities, Martin County Disaster, Kentucky (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - DEP Mining Regulation (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - DEP Standards for Resolving Violations (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - DEP Tour of Greene County, Aug 21, 2001 (Box 17, Folder 15)
  - Diagrams and Maps: Longwall Statistics (Box 17, Folder 16)
  - Dust (Box 17, Folder 17)
  - Environmental Justice Work Group (Box 17, Folder 18)
  - Fact Sheets (Box 17, Folder 19)
  - Full Cost Bonding (Box 17, Folder 20)
  - Global Warming (Box 17, Folder 21)
  - Governor Rendell (Box 17, Folder 22)
  - Grant Proposals, 2003 (Box 17, Folder 23)
  - Grant Proposal: Bonding Litigation, New Matler Form (Box 17, Folder 24)
  - Greene County (Box 17, Folder 25)
  - Greene County Power Plants (Box 17, Folder 26)
  - Handouts, 2001 (Box 17, Folder 27)
  - Historic Preservation (Box 17, Folder 28)
  - Hopey, Dan: Series on Greene County History and Grant Application (Box 17, Folder 29)
  - Imminent Hazard (Box 17, Folder 30)
  - Legislators and Other Contacts (Box 17, Folder 31)
  - Longwall Mining Publicity (Box 17, Folder 32)
  - LTV Steel (Box 17, Folder 33)
  - of Surface Mining Reclamation and Enforcement Annual Oversight Report, 2000 (Box 17, Folder 34)
  - Mercury (Box 17, Folder 35)
  - Methane Gas Drilling (Box 17, Folder 36)
  - News Clippings: Act 54, 2001 (Box 17, Folder 37)
  - Pennsylvania Environmental Network (PEN) (Box 17, Folder 38)
  - Penn Future (Box 17, Folder 39)
  - Pennsylvania Mining Reform Coalition (Box 17, Folder 40)
  - Plans for Legislative Tour (Box 17, Folder 41)
  - Senate Bill 1191: Coal Waste and Methane, Green Power (Box 17, Folder 42)
  - Septic Systems and Sewage (Box 17, Folder 43)
  - Sierra Club Environmental Justice Project and Appalachian Focu (Box 17, Folder 44)
  - Spreading the News on Longwall Mining: M. Plovic (Box 17, Folder 45)
  - Tri-State, 2005 (Box 17, Folder 46)
  - Undermined Surface Owners (Box 17, Folder 47)
  - Undermining: Interstates 70 and 79 (Box 17, Folder 48)
  - United Mine Workers (Box 17, Folder 49)
  - Video (Box 17, Folder 50)
  - Washington and Jefferson College Environmental Studies Program (Box 17, Folder 51)
  - Water (Box 17, Folder 52)